<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<channel><title>The Market Completionist</title><link>http://ejenk.com/blog</link>
<description>Thoughts on finance, economics, and beyond</description><language>en</language>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 12:20:57 -0600</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2014 12:20:57 -0600</pubDate>
<atom:link href="http://ejenk.com/blog/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<item><title>
Telling Stories about Market Corrections
</title><description><![CDATA[

<p>Much of the financial news over the past couple of weeks has centered on the question of whether the stock market is in the midst of a “correction.” The S&P 500 index peaked near 1,850 before taking a plunge which bottomed out near 1,740 (unless, of course, the gains of the last few days reverse themselves once again). A drop from 1,850 to 1,740 represents a 6% decline, which is huge when you consider that the market averages an increase of about 10% per year. So the analysts start trotting out stories about why this happened: the market was overvalued and was “due” to correct, investors got scared by a collapse of emerging market currencies, yadda yadda yadda. It’s easy to make up stories about why something happened in the past because nobody can tell you you’re wrong. I prefer the challenge of telling stories with enduring lessons to learn. Today’s story is about Brownian motion and why we should probably attribute market corrections to dumb luck.</p>

<hr />

<p>Before I begin the story, I want to spend a moment to talk to you about logarithms. I plan on devoting an entire post, or possibly several entire posts, to logarithms, but for now, let me just assure you that your life will become so much easier once you embrace the logarithm. So instead of thinking about the level of the S&P 500 index, let’s think of the log level. So our 6% (arithmetic) decline represents a change of \(\log(1 - .06) \approx -.062\) in the log level. The nearness of \(x\) and \(\log(1 + x)\) for small values of \(x\) is frustrating, because it makes it seem like there’s no difference between taking log changes and not. There’s a huge difference! If the market drops by 6% every month from now to eternity, we can just keep subtracting \(-.062\) from the log level, but you’ll be burdened with pesky multiplications if you try to remain arithmetic. So when we talk about the stock market from now on, we’ll mean the <em>log level</em> of the market.</p>

<p>One of the simplest and most enduring models of the stock market is as a Brownian motion with drift \(\mu\) and volatility \(\sigma^2\). The past tells us that \(\mu\) is about .10 per year, and \(\sigma^2\) is about \(.18^2\) per year. What this means is that our best guess for the level of the market \(t\) years from today is that it is normally distributed with a mean \(\mu t = .10t\) higher than it is now and a variance of \(\sigma^2 t = (.18)^2 t\). Now, let me make it clear that this model is wrong, not because continuous time and real numbers aren’t real (they aren’t, but that doesn’t really matter here), but because there are variables that can forecast expected returns, so our best guess is actually better than this. Nevertheless, the story of Brownian motion captures much of how we should think about the stock market over short time periods (days, weeks, months).</p>

<p>Now that we have a model, we can ask: how often should we expect a correction of a given magnitude? This is actually a pretty stupid question the way that the talking heads on CNBC think about it, because they’ll measure a correction from peak to trough. But what good is that to an investor, when you can’t know until after the fact that you’ve hit a peak or a trough? So let me start with a more fundamental question: what is the probability that at some point in the future the market will be down \(-.062\) from the price today? (Notice that this implies a larger correction from the peak, because with probability 1 you’ll see a higher market level before the drop! But let’s hold off on that disturbing thought for now.)</p>

<p>The way to approach this problem involves using a supremely valuable tool from the stochastic calculus toolbox: change of measure. Asking this sort of question for a driftless Brownian motion is easy: a driftless Brownian motion will always experience a \(-.062\) correction! So what we’ll do is we’ll just realize our Brownian motion with drift as just an ordinary driftless Brownian motion, but under a different measure.</p>

<p>We will write our market process in differential form as \[dX_t = \mu\,dt + \sigma\,dB^Q_t,\] where \(X_t\) is the (log) market level, and \(B_t\) is a standard Brownian motion with respect to a probability measure \(Q\). What we want is that the measure \(Q\) is equivalent to the standard measure \(P\) such that \(dX_t = \sigma dB^P_t\), where \(B^P_t\) is standard Brownian motion under \(P\). Plugging in \(\sigma dB^P_t\) for \(dX_t\) above gives \[\sigma dB^P_t = \mu\,dt + \sigma\,dB^Q_t,\]
or
\[dB^P_t = \frac{\mu}{\sigma} \,dt + dB^Q_t.\]</p>

<p>The magic wand we will wave over this is a result called the Girsanov theorem. In a nutshell, it says that if \(A_t\) is a sufficiently nice process, then we can find a change of measure such that \[dB^P_t = A_t\,dt + dB^Q_t.\]
Here we have the very special case where \(A_t\) is a constant, \(\frac{\mu}{\sigma}\). Girsanov tells us to construct a process \(M\) such that \[dM_t = A_tM_t\,dB^P_t, \quad M_0 = 1.\]
This stochastic differential equation has a simple solution, given by the so-called stochastic exponential: \[M_t = e^{\int_0^t A_s\,dB^P_s - \frac{1}{2}\int_0^t A_s^2\,ds}.\]
In our case, \(A_t = \frac{\mu}{\sigma}\), so this becomes
\[M_t = e^{\frac{\mu}{\sigma} B^P_t - \frac{\mu^2}{2\sigma^2} t}.\]
(Exercise: Use your mad Itō’s lemma skillz to check that this \(M\) satisfies the desired SDE.) With this process in hand, Girsanov tells us that, provided it is a martingale, the measures \(Q\) and \(P\) are related by \[\frac{dQ}{dP} = M_t\] for an arbitrary value of \(t\). (Another exercise: Show, using the assumption that \(M_t\) is a martingale, that the value of \(t\) doesn’t actually matter as long as we’re considering things at time \(s \leq t\). So we just take \(t\) to be as large as we need.)</p>

<p>Whew! Take a deep breath! Let’s remember what we’re trying to do: we want to find the \(Q\)-probability that our market process \(X_t\) dips below some level \(a\) (\(-.062\), for example). We’ve engineered things such that \(X_t = \sigma dB^P_t\). Let’s write \[T_a = \inf \{t \in \mathbb{R} \mid \sigma B^P_t = a\} = \inf \{t \in \mathbb{R} \mid B^P_t = \frac{a}{\sigma}\}.\] So our question is, what’s the \(Q\)-probability that \(T_a\) is finite? Well, let’s use the definition the Radon-Nikodym derivative: it’s \[E^P(M_{T_a} \mathbb{1}_{T_a < \infty}).\]
But we were clever! Under the measure \(P\), \(T_a\) is finite with probability 1, so we’re left with
\begin{align*}
Q(T_a < \infty) &= E^P(M_{T_a})\\
&= E^P\left(e^{\frac{\mu}{\sigma} B^P_{T_a} - \frac{\mu^2}{2\sigma^2} T_a}\right)\\
&= e^{\frac{\mu a}{\sigma^2}} E^P\left(e^{-\frac{\mu^2}{2\sigma^2} T_a} \right).
\end{align*}
Now, we could calculate the remaining expectation, but instead we’ll be sneaky. Observe that if the drift \(\mu\) has the same sign as \(a\), then the \(Q\)-probability has to be 1: of course the stock market will eventually produce a <em>gain</em> of 6%. So in this case, we must have \[ E^P\left(e^{-\frac{\mu^2}{2\sigma^2} T_a} \right) = e^{-\frac{\mu a}{\sigma^2}}.\]
But the expression on the left is indifferent to the sign of \(\mu\)! So in the case we’re interested in, where \(\mu\) and \(a\) have different signs, we must have
\[ E^P\left(e^{-\frac{\mu^2}{2\sigma^2} T_a} \right) = e^{\frac{\mu a}{\sigma^2}}.\]
Thus,
\[Q(T_a < \infty) = e^{\frac{\mu a}{\sigma^2}} \cdot e^{\frac{\mu a}{\sigma^2}} = e^{\frac{2 \mu a}{\sigma^2}}.\]</p>

<hr />

<p>Finally! The hard math is done, and we can reap our rewards. Plugging in \(\mu = .10\), \(\sigma = .18\), and \(a = -.062\), we see that the probability that the market will be 6% lower than it is now at some point in the future is a whopping 68%!  The probability of a 10% dip, which corresponds to a drop of \(-.105\), is 52%, still more likely than not. Eschewing my love of logarithms for a moment, below is a plot showing the probability that a given percentage drop will occur.</p>

<div align="center"><img src="marketdrop.png" width="500" height="500" /></div>

<p>What about the peak-to-trough question that the analysts love? One way to look at it is to notice that if we run the stock market backwards, it’s a Brownian motion with drift \(-\mu\) and the same volatility \(\sigma^2\). We can say that we’re in the midst of a peak-to-trough dip of size at least \(a\) if, looking backwards, we have an increase of \(a_1\), and looking forwards, we have a decrease of \(a_2\), where \(a_1 + a_2 > a\). Now, we notice that \(F(x) = 1 - e^{\frac{-2 \mu x}{\sigma^2}}\) (on the positive reals) is the cumulative density function for the probability distribution of having the biggest future drop be of size \(x\), and by symmetry, of having the biggest gain looking backwards be of size \(x\). So what we want is the probability that \(a_1 + a_2 > a\), where \(a_1\) and \(a_2\) are independent and distributed according to \(F\). This probability is
\begin{align*}
P(a_1 + a_2 > a) &= \int_{x + y > a} F'(x)F'(y)\,dx\,dy\\
&= \int_{0}^{\infty} F'(x) \int_{\max(a - x, 0)}^{\infty} F'(y)\,dy\,dx\\
&= \frac{2\mu}{\sigma^2} \int_{0}^{a} e^{\frac{-2 \mu a}{\sigma^2}}\,dx + \int_{a}^{\infty} F'(x)\,dx\\
&= e^{\frac{-2 \mu a}{\sigma^2}} \left(1 + \frac{2\mu a}{\sigma^2}\right).
\end{align*}</p>

<p>This brings us up to 92% for a 6% drop, and 86% for a 10% drop. What this means is that 92% of the time, the market is in the midst of a peak-to-trough drop of 6%. Note that the way we’ve calculated things does not exclude the possibility of a lower trough between the previous peak and now, or a higher peak between now and the trough. I’ll leave that one as an exercise. The probabilities of percentage drops are shown in the plot below.</p>

<div align="center"><img src="marketdrop2.png" width="500" height="500" /></div>

<p>So what have we shown here? If we allow ourselves to choose arbitrary endpoints, “correction” is the default state of the market. Half of the time, we can find a peak in the past and a trough in the future that represent a drop of at least 25%! If this seems impossible, let’s check it by looking at actual market data. I looked at monthly returns from 1963 to the present. This range has higher mean returns and lower standard deviation than my typical 10% and 18% (which I use because I like to be a conservative investor), which lowers the probabilities a bit. The plot below shows the probability of peak-to-trough drops from the model with drift and volatility taken from the data, as well as the actual observed frequencies.</p>

<div align="center"><img src="marketdrop3.png" width="500" height="500" /></div>

<p>The model greatly overestimates the probabilities of small drops. This is due to the fact that looking at monthly data, rather than instantaneous data, smooths out the peaks and troughs, which will lose a lot of the smaller ones. Also, the market may drop in the future, which would lead to an increase in drops over this timespan. But overall, the model looks like it fits pretty well! Let’s take a look at the time series, colored by the size of the peak-to-trough drop.</p>

<div align="center"><img src="marketdrop4.png" width="500" height="319" /></div>

<hr />

<p>So what we’ve shown is that when you measure corrections from a previous peak to a future trough, we’re almost always in a big correction. Even taking the more honest accounting of only looking at drops going forwards, you can still be pretty sure you’ll be down at least 5% or so from where you are now. You can tell yourself stories about scared investors or emerging market currencies, but ultimately, the existence of corrections is due to the high level of market volatility. The goal of financial analysis should be to explain that volatility directly, rather than to try to pick apart individual market fluctuations ex-post. Financial navel-gazing makes for good television, but it does little to help our understanding of markets.</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/telling-stories-about-market-corrections.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/telling-stories-about-market-corrections.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/telling-stories-about-market-corrections.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2014 22:03:35 -0600</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Life in an Incomplete Market
</title><description><![CDATA[

<p>I’ve already told you the beautiful story of <a href="/blog/complete-markets-a-fairy-tale.html">complete markets</a>, where we as rational investors perfectly hedge every idiosyncratic risk and share in every systemic one. Today I want to tell a slightly (but only slightly!) more realistic story, the story of incomplete markets.</p>

<hr />

<p>Recall that a <em>complete market</em> is one in which we can choose to hold a portfolio that gives any payoff we want in any state of nature. In other words, if \(\mathcal{S} = \{s_1, s_2, \ldots, s_n\}\) is the set of future states of nature, given any function \(x: \mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\), we can purchase assets that will give us a payoff of \(x(s_i)\) in the state \(s_i\). An <em>incomplete market</em> is one in which we only have access to a linear subspace of the vector space \(\mathbb{R}^{\mathcal{S}}\) of functions from \(\mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\). In other words, we can still hold any linear combination of assets, but there aren’t enough assets in existence to cover every possible contingency. This seems like a reasonable assumption to make: there are zillions of possible states of the world, but we can’t reasonably expect (or want) to bet on all of them.</p>

<p>The question, now, is how does a rational actor invest in this market? One way to answer this question is to consider all possible completions of this market. Let’s denote by \(V \subset \mathbb{R}^{\mathcal{S}}\) the subspace of payoffs that exist in our market. The market will have equilibrated to some linear price function \(p: V \to \mathbb{R}\). Now consider an extension \(\widetilde{p}: \mathbb{R}^{\mathcal{S}} \to \mathbb{R}\) of \(p\), that is, a way to linearly price new assets that keeps the prices of existing assets the same. There are many such extensions, as every time a new asset is introduced that is not a linear combination of old assets, it could in principle be given any price. Let’s denote by \(\mathcal{P}\) the set of all such extensions of our pricing function.</p>

<p>Let’s denote by \(U^{\ast}\) our maximum utility in the incomplete market, and by \(U^{\ast}_{\widetilde{p}}\) the maximum utility we could achieve in the market completed with the price function \(\widetilde{p}\). It’s clear that regardless of what \(\widetilde{p}\) is, we must have \(U^{\ast} \leq U^{\ast}_{\widetilde{p}}\): in the completed market, we can still buy anything we could buy in the incomplete market for the same price, so any utility we can achieve in the incomplete market we can also achieve in the complete market. Since this is true for any \(\widetilde{p} \in \mathcal{P}\), we have \[U^{\ast} \leq \inf_{\widetilde{p} \in \mathcal{P}} U^{\ast}_{\widetilde{p}}.\]</p>

<p>Now comes the exciting part of the story: the above inequality is actually an equality! In other words, in an incomplete market, we can achieve as much utility as the worst of all possible completions of that market. Why? Because for each new asset we can introduce, there will always be a price at which you’ll be indifferent towards it. If all of the new assets are given prices that make you indifferent, you might as well hold only old assets. So we conclude
\[U^{\ast} = \inf_{\widetilde{p} \in \mathcal{P}} U^{\ast}_{\widetilde{p}}.\]</p>

<hr />

<p>Let’s step back and think about what this says. How much utility are we losing by not having complete markets? It depends. If the “missing assets” are ones for which everybody would agree on the price, then we lose nothing, because nobody would bother buying them. Only in cases where the asset represents differing values for different agents do we feel the sting of incomplete markets. Insurance is important because we really care, moreso than most people, if our house burns down. From this perspective, stocks actually aren’t that important. Indeed, it’s one of the great mysteries of asset pricing why the stock market yields such a high premium!</p>

<p>Again, let me remind you not to take these fairy tales too seriously. After all, the assumption that we can buy any linear combination of assets (including those with negative coefficients!) is not a terribly realistic one. Nevertheless, we should take heart in the fact that this story, suprisingly, has a happy ending. It says that the most important assets to have in a market are the ones that will generate the most disagreement over their value. But this is precisely the kind of asset that markets are most likely to provide, since these generate the most profit. The extent to which markets are incomplete can therefore be divided along two lines: some assets aren’t being traded because it’s not worth the bother, and other assets aren’t traded because regulations make it either illegal or impractical to do so. On the other hand, lest you think I’ve turned libertarian, some markets that should exist don’t due to lack of government regulation: how many people bother with carbon credit markets? Not many, given that world governments aren’t terribly serious about curbing carbon emissions. Either way, it’s clear that governments play a central role in determining how complete our markets are.</p>

<p>In summary, life in an incomplete market isn’t so bad. To be precise, it’s only as bad as its worst completion. So when we encounter an incompleteness in our market, it’s important to ask ourselves why it’s there. Is it there because nobody would bother trading in it anyway, or is it there because of a failure in how markets are regulated? And if the answer is neither, you have a great opportunity to make some money!</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/life-in-an-incomplete-market.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/life-in-an-incomplete-market.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/life-in-an-incomplete-market.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 15:16:51 -0600</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Why You Shouldn’t Care About Preferences
</title><description><![CDATA[

<p>So you want to be a rational investor, eh? Congratulations, if you’re reading my blog, you’re already on the right track! One thing that might worry you, though, is all of those other crazies out there. After all, what good is it for you to be rational if the market is driven by a bunch of amped-up loonies on Wall Street? What if, as <a href="http://noahpinionblog.blogspot.com/2014/01/what-if-preferences-are-unstable.html">Noah Smith suggests</a>, other people’s investment decisions aren’t determined by a time-invariant concave utility function with hyperbolic discounting (heaven forbid!)? I’m here to tell you that it doesn’t matter. If your investment strategy depends on other people being rational, you’re doing it wrong.</p>

<p>In <a href="/blog/complete-markets-a-fairy-tale.html">my post on complete markets</a>, I gave you the magic formula for maximizing your utility in a complete market: \[\beta \frac{u'(c_{t + 1}(s_i))}{u'(c_t)} = m_i = \frac{p_i}{\pi_i}.\]
In words: we should tune our consumption such that our time-discounted relative marginal utility in each state of nature is equal \(m_i\), the ratio of the market price of a contingent claim on that state of nature to the probability of that state occurring.</p>

<p>Now, from the looks of this, other people’s preferences don’t come into play at all: as long as we understand our own preferences, we can just look at market prices to determine how much money to bet on each state. Unfortunately, this also requires us to know the probability \(\pi_i\) of each state. But how do we know what the right probabilities are? In the real world, we might use pricing information of derivatives to determine what the market thinks the probability of various events might be. But these probabilities are filtered through other people’s preferences! There seems to be no getting around it: after all, we need to use all of the market information just to get the numerator of \(m_i\), so we shouldn’t expect to squeeze anything else out to determine the denominator unless we make some extra modeling assumptions.</p>

<p>So it seems we’re at an impasse. Unless we have a crystal ball to tell us the probability distribution of future events, we may very well be at the whims of the loonies. But you know what? It doesn’t really matter. For the big stuff, like long-term savings, finance has developed some tools to tell us what kind of returns we should expect on a market portfolio. I’ll talk about these in future posts; they’re far from perfect, but they rely on data analysis rather than trying to model other people’s minds. For the other kind of big stuff, hedging our idiosyncratic risks, we have our own intuition about our situation to rely on, which is probably more accurate than a market’s guess anyway. In short, all of the probabilities we need to be estimating are ones that are best estimated from outside other people’s heads.</p>

<p>Trying to time the market and beat all of the suckers can be tempting. It can be fun. It can even be profitable! But let’s not call it rational investing. It’s gambling. Now, from a macro perspective, a bunch of loony gamblers can certainly have a deleterious effect on the market and on the wider economy. There are certainly reasons, from a policy perspective, to want to understand these effects. But that doesn’t mean we should jump in the loony bin with them! Loonies come and go, but in the long run, fundamentals drive the growth of our economy. When you invest, look at the prices and see if they seem cheap or expensive to you, not to some model that purports to know what other people are thinking. And as more people continue to forsake gambling for Vanguard index funds, the ride will only get smoother.</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/why-you-shouldnt-care-about-preferences.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/why-you-shouldnt-care-about-preferences.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/why-you-shouldnt-care-about-preferences.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 21:59:00 -0600</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Buffett’s Jackpot
</title><description><![CDATA[

<p>A fun finance-y story making the rounds is <a href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2014/01/21/1-billion-for-a-perfect-n-c-a-a-bracket-courtesy-of-warren-buffett/">Warren Buffett’s offer of $1 billion</a> for filling out a perfect NCAA bracket. Most of the analysis has focused on estimating the odds of winning (the general consensus: not good). But since I’ve been on an asset pricing kick, I want to talk about the misleading values attached to giant prizes and what this prize is actually worth.</p>

<p>As is the case with Powerball jackpots, Buffett’s prize is actually a choice of two prizes: if you want your full $1 billion, it will be paid out over 40 years in the form of a $25 million annual annuity. If you want a lump sum right now, you’ll have to settle for a mere $500 million. While the first choice nominally sums to $1 billion, you’re paying a huge opportunity cost to wait decades for much of that money. So which prize should you choose?</p>

<p>The value of the lump sum is easy enough to calculate: you get $500 million now, so it’s worth $500 million. (I’m going to ignore taxes for most of the rest of this discussion because I don’t know enough about how taxes work. My guess is that, given a competent accountant, taxes won’t disproportionately affect one choice vs. the other.) The value of the annuity is also not too bad to calculate, if we believe our lovely asset pricing formula, \(p = E(mx)\). First, let’s see how this formula behaves for an asset that always pays out the same amount, that is, for a <em>risk-free</em> asset. If I put $1 to a risk-free one-period bond at time \(t\), what should I expect it to pay me at time \(t + 1\)? Well, since the payoff \(x_{t + 1}\) is nonrandom, we can pull it out of the conditional expectation:
\[1 = E_t(m_{t + 1} x_{t + 1}) = x_{t + 1}E_t(m_{t + 1}),\]
so
\[x_{t + 1} = \frac{1}{E_t(m_{t + 1})}.\]
The payoff \(x_{t + 1}\) is called the <em>risk-free rate</em> and is typically denoted by \(R^f\). These days, interest rates are pretty low, but the historical average risk-free rate is around 4%, that is, \(R^f = 1.04\). Since we’re talking about the next 40 years, let’s just use this number.</p>

<p>So let’s look at the annuity’s payoff. It pays us $25 million each year for the next 40 years, so we can write \[x_{t + i} = d_{t + i} + p_{t + i},\]
where
\[d_{t + i} = \begin{cases}25 & \text{if $0 \leq i \leq 39$,}\\ 0 & \text{otherwise.}\end{cases}\]
In other words, we can treat the payoff at time \(t + i\) as the sum of the annuity payoff \(d_{t + i}\) and the value \(p_{t + i}\) of the remaining payoffs. Assuming we get our first payment right now (so we tack it on to our starting price), our total value telescopes out as
\begin{align*}
25 + p_t &= 25 + E_t(m_{t + 1}x_{t + 1})\\
&= 25 + 1.04^{-1}(25 + p_{t + 1})\\
&= 25 + 1.04^{-1}(25 + 1.04^{-1}(25 + p_{t + 2}))\\
&\vdots\\
&= \sum_{i = 0}^{39} 1.04^{-i} \times 25\\
&= \frac{1 - 1.04^{-40}}{1 - 1.04^{-1}} \times 25\\
&\approx 515.
\end{align*}
So there’s our answer: the lump sum is worth $500 million, while the annuity is worth $515 million, so we should take the annuity, right?</p>

<p>Not so fast. If you’re a semibillionaire with any ambition whatsoever, you’re not just going to stuff this money under your mattress (or worse, spend it!). With your newfound low risk-aversion, you’re going to want to plow your money into investments with a higher expected return than risk-free bonds. The stock market has historically returned more like 10%. Discount your annuity by 10% annually and it’s worth a measly $269 million!</p>

<p>But surely your annuity is worth more than that, right? After all, our formula shows that it’s actually worth $515 million, at least to somebody. The difficulty is finding that somebody. Here’s where things get a bit hazy, at least to me. Surely some giant financial firm would be willing to trade $515 million for your stream of future payments. But I’m not sure what the tax or legal implications of this are. What you won’t be able to find is somebody willing to lend you $515 million at a 4% annual rate, unless they can be sure that the loan really is risk-free: this means they would need your stream of annuity payments as collateral, which is the same as actually owning the annuity!</p>

<p>So my advice to you if you somehow win Warren Buffett’s money: hire some good lawyers and financial advisors to find out if you can feasibly sell your annuity. If you’re lucky, you might get a bit more than the lump sum. But either way, just know that you’re not even close to being a billionaire. So you’d better get your money to work!</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/buffetts-jackpot.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/buffetts-jackpot.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/buffetts-jackpot.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
Complete Markets: A Fairy Tale
</title><description><![CDATA[

<blockquote cite="http://arielrubinstein.tau.ac.il/Rubinstein2007.pdf">
<p>The word “model” sounds more scientific than “fable” or “fairy tale”, but I don’t see much difference between them. The author of a fable
draws a parallel to a situation in real life and has some moral he wishes
to impart to the reader. The fable is an imaginary situation that is
somewhere between fantasy and reality. Any fable can be dismissed
as being unrealistic or simplistic, but this is also the fable’s advantage.</p>

<p>—Ariel Rubinstein, <a href="http://arielrubinstein.tau.ac.il/Rubinstein2007.pdf">Lecture Notes in Microeconomic Theory: The Economic Agent</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>In <a href="/blog/what-is-finance.html">my previous post</a>, I mentioned that asset pricing was a wonderful language for storytelling. Today I’m going to tell a particularly moving story, the story of <em>complete markets</em>, which I learned in John Cochrane’s Coursera.</p>

<hr />

<p>Let’s go back to the main equation of asset pricing, \[p_t = E_t(m_{t + 1}x_{t + 1}).\] This says that the price I pay for an asset today is equal to its expected discounted payoff tomorrow. I stated this as a fact last time, but you should be at least a little suspicious: this is saying that for any asset you can imagine, there’s one discount factor \(m_{t + 1}\) that will price it. In other words, the same discount factor that I use to price Google stock will also work to price flood insurance. This is a bold claim! But in fact, we’ll see why it’s not really saying much at all. Let’s prove the existence of a discount factor for complete markets.</p>

<p>So what’s a complete market? The idea of finance, as I envisioned it in my previous post, is that you buy assets to hedge against future risks. You accept a negative expected return on your homeowner’s insurance because on the off chance your house burns down, you’ll really need the money. A <em>complete market</em> is one in which you can hedge against any risk. Let’s make this a bit more precise. Let’s suppose there’s a large, but finite, set \(\mathcal{S} = \{s_1, s_2, \ldots, s_n\}\) of all possible states of nature at time \(t + 1\). Each state \(s_i\) has a probability \(\pi_i\) of occuring. A complete market is one in which, at time \(t\), you can buy an asset that pays \(x(s_i)\) in the state \(s_i\), where \(x: \mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\) is any real-valued function on the set of states. For example, if you’re worried about your house burning down, you could buy an asset that pays out $150,000 in every state where your house burns down, and $0 otherwise. This should end up being fairly cheap, because the sum of the probabilities \(\pi_i\) of the states in which your house burns down at time \(t + 1\), which equals the total probability that your house burns down at time \(t + 1\), is small.</p>

<p>The astute reader will notice that the collection of asset payoffs in a complete market forms a vector space: you have one asset for each function \(x: \mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\). There’s a particularly nice basis for this vector space: for each state \(s_i\), we have the function \(\delta_i: \mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\) with \[\delta_i(s_j) = \begin{cases} 1 & \text{if $j = i$,}\\ 0 & \text{if $j \neq i$.}\end{cases}\] In other words, this function represents an asset that pays us $1 if we end up in state \(s_i\), and nothing otherwise. We call \(\delta_i\) a <em>contingent claim</em> on the state \(s_i\). The collection of all contingent claims forms a basis for the vector space of payoffs: we can write any payoff \(x: \mathcal{S} \to \mathbb{R}\) as a linear combination of contingent claims: \[x = \sum_{i = 1}^n x(s_i) \delta_i.\]</p>

<p>The point of identifying contingent claims as a basis is that any sensible way of pricing assets should be linear in the payoff: the price of a collection of two assets should be the sum of their prices, and the price of a scalar multiple of an asset should be the scalar multiple of that price. Without this assumption, there would be arbitrage opportunities. So to price any asset, it’s enough to know the price of each contingent claim. In other words, if the price of the contingent claim \(\delta_i\) is \(p_i\), then the price of the asset
\[x = \sum_{i = 1}^n x(s_i) \delta_i\]
will be
\[p(x) = p\left(\sum_{i = 1}^n x(s_i) \delta_i\right) = \sum_{i = 1}^n x(s_i) p(\delta_i) = \sum_{i = 1}^n x(s_i) p_i.\]
Now we do a bit of sleight of hand. We’d like to express the price of \(x\) as an expected discounted payoff. To do so, we need to introduce probabilities into the above sum. So we’ll multiply and divide each term by \(\pi_i\) and suggestively rearrange the factors:
\[p(x) = \sum_{i = 1}^n \pi_i \frac{p_i}{\pi_i} x(s_i).\]
So the contribution of each state to the price is the probability of the state, times the payoff of the state, discounted by a factor of \[m_i = \frac{p_i}{\pi_i}.\] So there it is, our discount factor \(m\)! I hope this result makes intuitive sense: the discount factor in a state is equal to how over- or under-priced a contingent claim on that state is compared to the probability of landing in that state.</p>

<hr />

<p>Now that we have the discount factor in hand, we can ask how an individual investor will act in this market. For simplicity, we’re going to assume that this individual is only alive at times \(t\) and \(t + 1\), so they’ll spend all their money while they can. This may seem like a silly assumption, but it makes the notation easier without actually losing any of the story.</p>

<p>Let’s say our individual has a wealth of \(w\). What they want to do is maximize their utility \(u(c_t)\) of consuming some of that wealth now, plus their expected discounted utility \(\beta E_t(u(c_{t + 1}))\) of investing the rest to consume a time \(t + 1\). We can think of the consumption \(c_{t + 1}\) as representing the asset, called the <em>consumption claim</em>, that we invest in at time \(t\) to pay for our future consumption. We write the wealth constraint on this optimization as \[c_t + p_t(c_{t + 1}) = w.\] Notice that this optimization problem has \(n + 1\) variables: how much we consume today, and the \(n\) state weightings \(c_{t + 1}(s_i)\) of our consumption claim. We can write the price of the consumption claim in terms of these variables as \[p_t(c_{t + 1}) = \sum_{i = 1}^n c_{t + 1}(s_i) p_i.\]</p>

<p>I’ll leave it as an exercise for the reader to check using Lagrange multipliers that we get maximal utility plus expected discounted utility precisely when, for each \(i\),
\[\beta \frac{u'(c_{t + 1}(s_i))}{u'(c_t)} = m_i.\]
This result is mind-blowing and deep: what it’s saying is that in a complete market, a rational utility-maximizer will buy assets in such a way as to make their personal discount factor, which depends on their utility function, equal to the discount factor \(m\) of the market, which was imputed from pricing information. This holds even if we put additional variables like leisure or the joys of homeownership into our utility function. A rational investor will choose to share fully in all systemic market risks and opportunities and hedge fully against their own idiosyncratic risks and opportunities. A rational investor will hedge against the loss of their house, but not try to invest countercyclically to hedge against recessions. Likewise, a rational investor should hedge, in the other direction, against getting a raise, or a local increase in housing values, but not against widespread economic booms. In an economy of rational investors, all risk and all opportunity is shared.</p>

<hr />

<p>Let’s step back. On the one hand, this story is crazy: it’s obviously not how the world works. People, even very smart ones, do take on idiosyncratic risks and fail to hedge idiosyncratic opportunities. But like any good fairy tale, it doesn’t matter whether or not it’s true. The point is the moral of the story. Regular people do engage in this sort of hedging. They hedge risks by carrying insurance, and they hedge prospects of future raises by borrowing and spending beyond their current means. While they might not be doing these things in a completely optimal way, they can hardly be blamed, given that complete markets and perfect information don’t really exist. What the idea of complete markets provides is a platonic ideal for how people, businesses, and governments can try to put themselves on a sound financial path.</p>

<p>The story of complete markets also teaches us a very important lesson about wealth inequality: we shouldn’t simply expect poor people to pull themselves up by their bootstraps, when even the platonic ideal of a rational person will only get rich in proportion to the broader economy. Taking this idea seriously, of course, requires a somewhat broader conception of “wealth,” wherein a person who is poor in cash but rich in ability can borrow against the future earnings that ability can generate. But even if everybody were able to cash in on their future earning potential, poverty would still exist. But I’ll leave the question of how finance can deal with this problem to a future post!</p>

<p>But I like the story of complete markets for a very selfish reason: it proved me right! I mentioned last time that I naïvely thought a “hedge fund” was something you used to hedge against your own idiosyncratic risks, when in fact the word “hedge” refers to systemic risks. But the complete markets story says that this is exactly the wrong way to invest! We can increase our expected utility by hedging idiosyncratic risks because those risks mean more to us than to the market as a whole. But there’s no point to trying to swim upstream against the market: the rational investor fully shares all systemic risks, albeit at a level determined by their personal risk-averseness.</p>

<hr />

<p>I’ve dubbed myself the Market Completionist because I believe that many (though, as I mentioned above, not all) economic problems can be transformed into the same question: <em>How do we complete this market?</em> In incomplete markets, renters have to worry about gentrification pushing them out of their homes. In incomplete markets, workers have to be worried about getting laid off. In incomplete markets, the uninsured (now fewer in number, of course) have to worry about a trip to the ER bankrupting them. Problems like these are often solved by inefficient government regulation, which obscures the true costs involved in hedging our idiosyncratic risks. Having transparent and accessible market mechanisms is virtually always going to lead to better outcomes. The irony is that the one thing the government is best at, which is redistributing wealth to those who need it, is the one thing that’s completely taboo to suggest. As a result, much of this redistribution is bundled into regulations that often end up helping a small group of people at the expense of everybody else.</p>

<p>Now let me, *ahem*, hedge what I just said. There’s a good reason Complete-Market Libertopia doesn’t exist yet: markets are hard to do right! Many government safeguards against risk exist for a very good reason: having an appropriate risk-sharing market would simply be infeasible. But one doesn’t need to be a transhumanist to see that technology is making it easier and easier to have good, powerful markets. Fifty years ago, investing in the stock market meant paying a big commission to a broker to purchase paper shares of individual companies that you would then lock up in a safe. Today you can sign up on <a href="http://www.vanguard.com/">Vanguard</a>, click a few links, and own a representative portfolio of the US stock market. Fifty years ago, giving government workers pensions made total sense. These days, not so much.</p>

<p>Markets have gotten a bad name in recent years. The people who were supposed to be experts in markets ended up crashing the economy into the ground. If experts can’t handle market-based risk management correctly, what hope is there for the rest of us? But the beauty of markets is choice, and if we like simplicity and safety, the market will provide it. This is why Vanguard funds have become so popular. If you want to treat the stock market like a casino, you can make things arbitrarily complicated for yourself. But if you set realistic financial goals, make an honest assessment of the big idiosyncratic risks you need to hedge, and keep a handle on your consumption, living a financially stable life doesn’t need to be a big chore. And I’m optimistic that technological advances and social progress will continue to broaden access to the power of markets and help people live better lives.</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/complete-markets-a-fairy-tale.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/complete-markets-a-fairy-tale.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/complete-markets-a-fairy-tale.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate></item>
<item><title>
What Is Finance?
</title><description><![CDATA[

<p>Last spring, I was trying to figure out what to do with my life. For many years, I had been operating on autopilot: I was going to finish my PhD and spend the rest of my days in the secluded comfort of the ivory tower, researching and teaching mathematics, the subject that had been coursing through my veins from infancy. I was slow to catch on to the reality that I was not enjoying my research, not enjoying my teaching, and increasingly unable to see a future where I would be enjoying those things. I won’t torture you with the hows and whys, but I had reached a dead end.</p>

<p>It seems almost trite that I decided to pursue finance. After all, finance is the perfect industry for somebody with high-powered academic credentials and not a single clue. At least, it was before 2008. These days, fallen academics are increasingly rushing to the tech world as financial firms are operating with less abandon than one might be led to believe. As a result, I probably come off as even more clueless than I actually am: if I want to be a quant, I should probably hop in a time machine.</p>

<p>But for some reason, finance beckoned to me in a way tech never did. I was becoming increasingly aware of the ways in which the good and the bad in the world could be explained by economic considerations. From the state of our built environment, which I had become <a href="http://letthemidwaybloom.wordpress.com/">very passionate about</a>, to global warming, economics was, to paraphrase Homer Simpson, the cause of, and solution to, all of life’s problems.</p>

<p>Finance, as I understood the term, had something to do with economics, so naturally I was curious. But there was one simple question that I found surprisingly difficult to answer: What is finance?</p>

<hr />

<p>My first inkling of what finance is came from arguing with people about the cult of homeownership following the collapse of the housing bubble. We tend to massively subsidize owning a home, both on the national level through the mortgage interest tax deduction, and on the local level through <a href="http://marketurbanism.com/2012/07/01/why-do-condos-even-exist/">tax codes and various regulations</a>. Here’s a little libertarian koan for you: if homeownership is so important, why does the government have to subsidize it?</p>

<p>People tend to cite two factors in favor of homeownership. First, they say, buying a home is an investment. Your mortgage payments go to owning something, whereas you’ll never see your rental payments again. We subsidize homeownership in order to encourage good investment. Second, homeowners will care more about their community because they have more invested in it. If your community improves, the value of your house will go up, which is good for you. On the other hand, renters might oppose improvements for fear that their rent will go up. So homeownership is worth subsidizing because it creates positive externalities for the community.</p>

<p>Let’s deconstruct these arguments one at a time. The first can be pretty easily dispatched with. A home is a <em>terrible</em> investment for most people. Let’s first note that it’s a highly leveraged one unless you choose to buy outright. Traditionally, people put 20% down, which means leveraging 4-to-1. During in the housing bubble, it became fashionable to put less, or even none down. But even the baseline 4-to-1 is still quite leveraged: a 10% drop in your home’s value will halve your equity, and a 20% drop will annihilate it. Unless you truly believe the now-disproven notion that home prices will keep rising forever, a 20%-down mortgage is a massively risky investment.</p>

<p>Even ignoring the extra risk involved in leveraging, the returns look somewhat suspect as well. There are two parts to your investment: the land your home sits on, and the building itself. (We’ll ignore the puzzle of condos, where you in principle own a share of the land, but in practice have no way to cash in on it.) Land is certainly something that can appreciate greatly in value if you live in a desirable location: supply in your area is fixed, and demand will keep rising as long as your location stays desirable. Unfortunately, the desirability of your location is very likely positively correlated to your income. If you’re living in an industry hotbed, your job is very likely secure, so you don’t need your investment to rise as much. But if things take a turn for the worse, you might lose your job, only to discover that your house isn’t worth the paper your mortgage is printed on. In short, unless your occupation happens to be terribly countercyclical, the land where you live is exactly the kind of investment you don’t want to be highly leveraged in.</p>

<p>The other portion of your investment is the building itself. This isn’t so much an investment as a liability. Buildings, particularly ones that are lived in, need to be maintained, insured, and kept up to code. Put that on top of the land, which as we saw was already a dubious investment, and you just have something awful.</p>

<p>But what about renting? Isn’t it still true that when you buy a home, you should at least see <i>some</i> of that money back, whereas rental money is gone forever? To answer that, we have to understand exactly what your rental money is paying for. Your landlord owns the land your building is on. Land, as we said, can potentially be a good investment. So why bother maintaining a building at all? To amortize construction costs and pay for maintenance, insurance, taxes, and utilities, your landlord needs something in return. Those costs are precisely the costs you pay for when you own your home, but a landlord can likely manage them much more efficiently than you can! In sparsely populated areas, the overhead can be too great, which explains why you mostly see rentals in urban areas. But really, the only reason that we should see rental costs above what you might expect to pay owning a home (modulo perhaps the amount of DIY labor you wish to put in) is because we do so heavily subsidize owning over renting!</p>

<p>Now that we’ve broken down the investment myth using a bit of financial thinking, let’s move to the community myth. This one is a bit trickier because there seems to be a kernel of truth to it. Renters certainly don’t want their rents to go up. While in principle, a homeowner should want the value of their house to go up, this also means that their property taxes go up. Since most people tend to think very short-term about their finances (even though the homeowner mindset is supposed to be a hedge against this), aversion to higher taxes probably tends to lump homeowners in the same camp as renters.</p>

<p>This is not good! People should be able to benefit from improvements to their community. They should want progress, development, and wealth. But both this thought exercise and real-world experience tells us that renters and owners alike tend to oppose such niceties. But at least we’ve debunked the community myth: renters and owners alike do not want to improve their communities.</p>

<hr />

<p>So far, we’ve used finance to make observations about how the world works, and what we’ve observed should disturb us deeply. We’ve seen that homeowners are making terrible, risky investments, and our communities are languishing because allowing communities to flourish is not in residents’ self-interest. But finance is more than just an observational tool: it is a creative framework. We can use financial reasoning not only to identify problems but to correct them.</p>

<p>A very basic example of a financial solution is homeowner’s insurance. Without it, owning a home would be an even risker proposition than I’ve outlined above. People understand why they need insurance: if their home burned down without it, they’d be destitute.</p>

<p>The reason insurance works is that people are willing to give up a small amount of money to avoid a big, if unlikely, risk. But in order for this deal to be profitable for the insurer, the small amount of money has to be greater than the insurer’s expected payout. Both sides are happy because you are more sensitive to the risk than the insurer, who can afford to pay to rebuild your house after a fire because they’ve been receiving premiums from lots of other people who don’t need to rebuild. Things like flood insurance are much more tricky, because floods tend to affect a lot of houses at once, so insuring a bunch of houses in the same area would expose an insurer to massive risk.</p>

<p>If homeowners buy insurance to protect against losing their house in a fire, then why shouldn’t they also buy insurance to protect against the value of their house going down due to decreased demand? Indeed, a number of such schemes appeared in the wake of the housing crisis, but <a href="http://www.bizjournals.com/sanfrancisco/blog/2012/08/home-value-insurance-real-estate-venture.html?page=all">consumers didn’t bite</a> and <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/realestate/home-value-insurance-were-not-convinced-its-a-good-idea/2012/05/23/gJQAgMpXpU_story.html">pundits remain skeptical</a>. One reason to be very skeptical of such a product is that it suffers from the same problem as flood insurance, but worse: in 2008 we saw housing prices plummet across most of the US.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, finance may still be able to provide a solution. Rather than purchasing insurance, a savvy homeowner could in principle participate in a <a href="http://www.cmegroup.com/trading/real-estate/files/spcaseshiller_fact_card.pdf">Case-Shiller Home Price Index futures market</a>. While financial derivative markets are typically only available to institutional investors, there’s no reason in principle that the power of such markets could not be brought to homeowners. Buying put options for the Case-Shiller Home Price Index is nearly equivalent to buying home value insurance, but potentially with less overhead and systemic risk.</p>

<p>In the interest of keeping the length of this introductory post (relatively) short, I’ll put off a discussion of how finance can solve the more thorny community problem to a future post. But I hope that I’ve laid out the basic idea: financial instruments like insurance and futures contracts exist to hedge risks. If an investment seems too good to be true, like houses did during the bubble, it’s probably because you haven’t considered the cost of hedging all the risk. Gambling can be fun, but when it comes to how we should run our lives, it seems prudent to not allow ourselves more risk than we’re willing to bear.</p>

<hr />

<p>Everything I’ve said so far is what I thought finance should be. In reality, it’s largely a gambler’s world. Still, it seems, there’s value in learning to navigate this world. I heard through the Twitter grapevine that <a href="http://johnhcochrane.blogspot.com/">John Cochrane</a> was going to be teaching an asset pricing course on <a href="http://coursera.org/">Coursera</a>, so I dove in. Thanks to John’s wonderfully lucid course, I’ve learned a little bit about what finance is. There are many beautiful stories written in the language of asset pricing, so I want to start by reviewing some of the vocabulary and then move on to some simple tales.</p>

<p>An asset, I believe, is something we buy that has no intrinsic value to us; all that matters is how much money it will return to us in the future. Already, this is a problematic definition, particularly when we apply it to something like a house, but even when we apply it to things like gold and Bitcoin and other investments that people tend to have more than a strict emotional detachment to. But I digress.</p>

<p>The central question of asset pricing is, unsurprisingly, what is the price of an asset? The answer takes a very nice form: \[p_t = E_t(m_{t + 1}x_{t + 1}).\]
What this equation says is that the <em>price</em> \(p_t\) of an asset at time \(t\) is equal to the expected value (using only the information we have at time \(t\)) of the <em>discounted payoff</em> at the future time \(t + 1\). The <em>payoff</em> \(x_{t + 1}\) is the value of whatever our asset has turned into. If we’re pricing a stock, for instance, we could write \[x_{t + 1} = d_{t + 1} + p_{t + 1},\] where \(d_{t + 1}\) is a <em>dividend</em> that’s paid directly to us, and \(p_{t + 1}\) is how much our stock is now worth. The <em>discount factor</em> \(m_{t + 1}\) is more mysterious. It expresses the fact that an amount of money at time \(t + 1\) might be worth less or more to us than that same amount of money at time \(t\).</p>

<p>A fundamental model for the discount factor \(m_{t + 1}\) is the <em>consumption-based model</em>. In this model, \(m_{t + 1}\) splits up into the product of two factors: a <em>future discounting constant</em> \(\beta\), which describes how much we prefer money now to money later, and a <em>coefficient of relative risk aversion</em> \[\dfrac{u'(c_{t + 1})}{u'(c_t)},\] which describes how risk averse we at time \(t + 1\) relative to time \(t\). Observe that \[m_{t + 1} = \beta \dfrac{u'(c_{t + 1})}{u'(c_t)}\] is a <em>stochastic discount factor</em>: it depends on a variable, <em>consumption</em> at time \(t + 1\), that we don’t know at time \(t\), so its exact value is not known to us.</p>

<p>A basic fact we can observe from this formula is that we will prefer (i.e., be willing to pay more for) assets that pay out in bad times to assets that pay out in good times. This lets us restate our explanation of why insurance works: we are willing to accept a negative expected payoff for insurance because it pays us precisely when we need it most. The insurance company, which is more or less indifferent to the state of your house, only cares that it’s getting a positive expected payoff from selling you that insurance. The market works not because the market participants have different information, but because they have differing risk aversions.</p>

<p>This is the brand of finance I envisioned above: you can hedge risks by trading with somebody who is not exposed to them. Indeed, this is what I naïvely imagined a “hedge fund” to be! Instead, the “hedge” in “hedge fund” apparently refers purely to hedging drops in the market, and in practice, it’s meaningless. In practice, hedge funds aren’t trying to exploit differences between their discount factors and the composite “market” discount factor; rather, they are trying to find situations in which the basic pricing equation, \(p = E(mx)\), is wrong, assets that have for whatever reason been systemically mispriced. This explanation may yet be too kind: in the absence of mispricing, you can always gamble and try to cleverly hide the risks for as long as possible. Exploiting mispricings corrects them, and thus it serves an important function. Gambling does not. Determining who’s doing what is not, looking from the outside, an easy task.</p>

<hr />

<p>At heart, I’m an idealist. That’s why I’ve spent most of this post giving my aspirational view of what finance is, or rather, what I want finance to be. But I’m willing to get down and dirty with the gamblers not just to pay the bills, but more importantly to see how the financial system really works. I’ll probably spend quite a few more blog posts riffing on the “what is finance” theme, since if I haven’t made it clear over the past 2,600 words, I’m still pretty hazy on the concept. I hope you’ll stick with me to see if I ever figure it out!</p>
<!-- text end -->
<p id='twitter'>Comments?&nbsp;
<a href="https://twitter.com/share" class="twitter-share-button" data-text="&lt;Type your comment here but please leave the URL so that other people can follow the comments&gt;" data-url="http://ejenk.com/blog/what-is-finance.html"
 data-via="ejenk"
>Tweet</a>	<script>!function(d,s,id){var js,fjs=d.getElementsByTagName(s)[0];if(!d.getElementById(id)){js=d.createElement(s);js.id=id;js.src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js";fjs.parentNode.insertBefore(js,fjs);}}(document,"script","twitter-wjs");</script>
</p>
]]></description><link>http://ejenk.com/blog/what-is-finance.html</link>
<guid>http://ejenk.com/blog/what-is-finance.html</guid>
<dc:creator>Evan Jenkins</dc:creator>
<pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate></item>
</channel></rss>
